window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Operating_System - Memory_Management — Slot 5 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Memory_Management — Slot 5",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>A page fault <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Occurs when a program accesses an available page on memory</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is an error in a specific page</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is a reference to a page belonging to another program</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>occurs when a program accesses a page not currently in memory</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>occurs when a program accesses a page not currently in memory</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50331/isro2009-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>A multilevel page table is preferred in comparison to a single level page table for\ntranslating virtual address to physical address because <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>It reduces the memory access time to read or write a memory location.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>It helps to reduce the size of page table needed to implement the virtual address space of a process.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>It is required by the translation lookaside buffer.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>It helps to reduce the number of page faults in page replacement algorithms.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>It helps to reduce the size of page table needed to implement the virtual address space of a process.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1320/gate2009-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The essential content(s) in each entry of a page table is / are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Virtual page number</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Page frame number</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both virtual page number and page frame number</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Access right information</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Page frame number</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1302/gate2009-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>In which one of the following page replacement policies, Belady's anomaly may occur? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>FIFO</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Optimal</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>LRU</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>MRU</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>FIFO</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1301/gate2009-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The page replacement algorithm which gives the lowest page fault rate is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>LRU</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>FIFO</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Optimal page replacement</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Second chance algorithm</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Optimal page replacement</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50133/isro2008-67\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider a logical address space of 8 pages of 1024 words mapped into memory of 32 frames. How many bits are there in the logical address? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>13 bits</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>15 bits</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>14 bits</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>12 bits</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>13 bits</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50005/isro2008-65\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Overlaying <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>requires use of a loader</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>allows larger programs, but requires more effort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is most used on large computers</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>is transparent to the user</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>allows larger programs, but requires more effort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/47809/isro2008-60\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Dirty bit for a page in a page table <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>helps maintain LRU information</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>allows only read on a page</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2241/gate1997-3-10-isro2008-57-isro2015-64\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Thrashing <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>always occurs on large computers</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is a natural consequence of virtual memory systems</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>can always be avoided by swapping</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>can be caused by poor paging algorithms</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>can be caused by poor paging algorithms</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/17260/isro2008-53\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Dynamic address translation <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>is part of the operating system paging algorithm</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is useless when swapping is used</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is the hardware necessary to implement paging</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>storage pages at a specific location on disk</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>is the hardware necessary to implement paging</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/17262/isro2008-52\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Match the following flag bits used in the context of virtual memory management on the left side with the different purposes on the right side of the table below.<br>\\(\\begin{array}{l|ll} \\text { Name of the bit } &amp; \\text { Purpose } \\\\ \\hline \\text { I. } \\text { Dirty } &amp; \\text { a. }  \\text { Page initialization } \\\\ \\text { II. } \\text { R/W } &amp; \\text { b. } \\text { Write-back policy } \\\\ \\text { III. } \\text { Reference } &amp; \\text { c. } \\text { Page protection } \\\\ \\text { IV. } \\text { Valid } &amp; \\text { d. } \\text { Page replacement policy } \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\text{I-d, II-a, III-b, IV-c}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\text{I-b, II-c, III-a, IV-d}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\text{I-c, II-d, III-a, IV-b}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\text{I-b, II-c, III-d, IV-a}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\text{I-b, II-c, III-d, IV-a}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3366/gate2008-it-56\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Assume that a main memory with only 4 pages, each of 16 bytes, is initially empty. The CPU generates the following sequence of virtual addresses and uses the Least Recently Used (LRU) page replacement policy.<br>\n0, 4, 8, 20, 24, 36, 44, 12, 68, 72, 80, 84, 28, 32, 88, 92 <br>\nHow many page faults does this sequence cause? What are the page numbers of the pages present in the main memory at the end of the sequence? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>6 and 1, 2, 3, 4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>7 and 1, 2, 4, 5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>8 and 1, 2, 4, 5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9 and 1, 2, 3, 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>7 and 1, 2, 4, 5</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3351/gate2008-it-41\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>A paging scheme uses a Translation Look-aside Buffer (TLB). A TLB-access takes 10 ns and the main memory access takes 50 ns. What is the effective access time(in ns) if the TLB hit ratio is 90% and there is no page-fault? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>54</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>60</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>65</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>75</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>65</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3276/gate2008-it-16\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A processor uses 36 bit physical addresses and 32 bit virtual addresses, with a\npage frame size of 4 Kbytes. Each page table entry is of size 4 bytes. A three\nlevel page table is used for virtual to physical address translation, where the\nvirtual address is used as follows <br><br>\nBits 30-31 are used to index into the first level page table <br>\nBits 21-29 are used to index into the second level page table <br>\nBits 12-20 are used to index into the third level page table, and <br>\nBits 0-11 are used as offset within the page <br><br>\nThe number of bits required for addressing the next level page table (or page\nframe) in the page table entry of the first, second and third level page tables are\nrespectively <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>20, 20 and 20</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>24, 24 and 24</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>24, 24 and 20</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>25, 25 and 24</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>25, 25 and 24</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/490/gate2008-67#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The minimum number of page frames that must be allocated to a running process in a virtual memory environment is determined by <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>the instruction set architecture</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>page size</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>number of processes in memory</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>physical memory size</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>the instruction set architecture</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1018/gate2004-21-isro2007-44\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
